I was going to start by asking you to tell you how you got into the thought
That you would plug in at all.
Do Ellika want to start?
My career change has been based on the fact that I want to be involved and influence more
And work on development issues, leadership issues, knowledge issues - -
And it was so important for me to do it with a high quality -
that I quickly landed in that I really want to have my feet -
If I am going to work on these types of questions.
When I with the help of coaches began to look at which courses existed
And quickly found this one, I saw that it was so wide -
And had so much of the pieces that I wanted to supplement with ...
So yeah, it was pretty obvious even though it wasn't the first thing i thought
It began as a reaction to me getting a mission
As course leader at the School of Music where I got more to bite in -
Even I was used to in the orchestra ditch as a fluteist.
It attracted my desire
To learn more about organization and development work.
When I then saw the opportunity with the Sok Foundation -
set it off quite a lot of thoughts, and soon I landed in -
That the staff and work life program would be exciting and fun.
An exciting education
With all different orientations.
The interdisciplinary in it.
Since then I have always been curious about what is happening
It's so nice, because it's about why you plug.
The older you get, the more your choice is about who you are
And what abilities you have.
Many people start their song and music career very young ...
I started playing violin when I was five and from eighteen it was singing.
I bought all the concepts with holes and hair.
My choice when I was over 40 was much more based on who I have become
And I didn't buy any finished concept.
I think it is a very favorable breeding ground for learning
Learning from one's own desire and curiosity to develop.
What else should life be about when we live for so long
Should we just stagnate the older we become it is an old thinking -
From when you died at 55-60 and worn out from 40.
So it doesn't look today.
We actually have to fill our lives with something meaningful.
Learning new makes you feel more vital, and it opens new worlds.
It may happen that it takes a half hour extra to plug in certain things
But you have completely different experiences to hang it up and do it out of desire.
You should not underestimate that.
And one's role in the importance of that work.
The training has been amazing
and the opportunity to delve into the different pieces at all -
which is pedagogy, sociology, psychology and even
Finance and labor law.
It has been a lot of fun.
Did you have fears about you would not be able to do with pace
Or have enough data competence, or was there any resistance in you before?
The digital competence became alert that one must switch up
In relation to what you do when working as a musician -
And it is an important part to absorb if you are going to do a career change -
or broaden their knowledge.
There you will not get away!
This bit with group work in a team
Have we really worked with for so many years -
Maybe without thinking so much consciously about it.
But precisely the discipline and ability to focus
Think I'm the biggest pieces that are a big plus.
But you have to see it too, maybe get help from a counselor or coach ...
"Think of all this that you can" "Yes, just that!"
... to strengthen their self -confidence and be able to have the courage to take the step.
Did it feel scary when you took the step?
-Yes actually!
To voluntarily resign and do this instead was very big.
And many were surprised: "are you really going to do this"
So that you do not make too quick a decision.
For me, it was important to be able to bounce the pros and cons with myself.
Because it should be sustainable too.
You should not think after three years: "What did I do"
... and longing back.
Without it, it must be a well -considered decision.
And the advisers and even a coach that helped me at the beginning
by structuring the thoughts ...
It is an invaluable help that you should not hesitate to take.
Even if one does not take the step fully
Without just wanting to nose on what help there is to get -
Is it good to contact the SOK Foundation and talk about it.
Air their thoughts.
How was it for you when you ... made the decision
It's almost that you don't remember it now.
But I thought about what you said about what you have with you from your professional life ...
One should not underestimate one's habit of entering a professional role
that there are very high demands on professionalism within opera.
It requires everyone to know their thing and does it in the right place at the right time.
It requires discipline and entering the professional role required right here.
You have tremendous training on that.
You can flame one second and then focus!
One should not underestimate
that it is a huge quality to have with you whatever one does -
That you are used to delivering, focusing and doing everything with quality.
Working life today also looks so different than 2025 years ago.
Then they stayed longer in the same profession.
Having the humble attitude helps a lot, and they feel that.
The teachers also talked a lot about having a mixed class
With different ages and life experiences.
It is very rewarding.
I get such respect for the knowledge of these young people
And their point of view.
You get many perspectives with them -
that are valuable.
To get them so close.
You sit next to each other in the benches and discuss.
You get a task from the teacher and have a snack.
It depends more on who you are as a person and what attitude you have.
We define so much by age and profession in many contexts.
than that you are very fixed to it.
With a slightly higher age you can actually contribute with a calm.
I can remember myself from the age that one became very stressed out
over exams and things to be delivered.
I should not say that I have not been nervous
But you have a different experience and can't cope with everything -
And life is so complex.
So I feel that we can contribute:
"Now we do this, it will be fine. Think about this ..."
Then you can both give and take, when you contribute your experience.
Yes, that last ...
It's also so fun in this education ...
And that one can see it as an opportunity instead of a compulsion
Yes absolutely.
Learning new is so much about changing the perspective
Or see several perspectives.
It may have been the clearest lesson -
Even in this education with many perspectives with different subject areas.
And it's fun to have the opportunity to widen the world in some way.
And also understand the context: what does the opera mean in society
And what does culture in society mean, etc.
When working at an institution you easily become like a large family
But don't really have all the perspectives you could have.
And I feel that is a lovely, fun and exciting insight.
If you were to be invited to a staff party at Malmö Opera
and meet colleagues who wonder:
"To plug when you have a career behind it is worth it"
"Should I do that what do you think?"
If someone asks, I think about being curious: "Dare"
Another important thing is to work with the idea of widening their network.
Not only to spend time with like -minded
And in this way also challenge itself.
To have a circle of friends with many different people and occupational categories
Have probably aroused the desire to learn and dare to take the step for me.
But ... just the courage to dare to take the step.
Working as we do means that you have to choose a lot in your life.
You have to focus.
If there is anything else as you thought:
"Wondering what it's like to work with it ..."
"I would have liked to use this side of myself more ..."
"I'm a little worn out just working on this part of my abilities ..."
... then there is something to pick up there.
Then one can start widening their picture of what this something is
By taking a lunch with someone working on it.
Like traveling to another continent: you know you want to go there but no more.
Then you start reading books, watch some movie and ask someone who has been there
And suddenly you have booked the ticket and are there.
It is such a type of process.
There is some seed in one because you do this.
You do this because you want something.
But it's all about widening, and it may take some time
Because you have been here: "How do I perform best tonight?"
It is perhaps what life has been a lot about
To make a really good performance tomorrow.
But if someone would ask: "Do you think I would be able to plug"
Yes, but God.
Yes